Give me your census record
戶口名簿拿來
You have seven people in your family
哦 你們家有七口
What about yours?
哦 你家幾口
There are five in my home
我家五口
More
多點
Seven!
七口啊
Thanks!
謝謝
Go over there
你去那裏領
Granny, come here please
阿婆在這邊
Where is your record consensus?
你戶口名簿呢
"Jesus! Jesus! No rice to eat."
耶穌 耶穌 沒米可以吃
"Climb on the trees to eat sweet potato."
爬到樹上吃蕃薯塊
"God! God! Give us food."
上帝 上帝 賜我們吃
"Give us dress, give us shit..."
賜我們穿 賜我們放屎
The church is sharing flour, hurry
基督教在發麵粉 快去啦
OK!
哦
Hurry!
你還不趕快去
A-chu! What's wrong with A-long?
阿珠啊 阿龍是怎麼樣啦
Nothing!
沒有啦
Nothing! Nothing, then what's this?
沒有 沒有 這是什麼
You've no idea, it's mine
你不知道啦 這是我吃的
It's yours! What's wrong with you?
你吃的 你怎麼啦
You are not well?
人不舒服
You got a loop?
哦 你去裝樂普
I told you many times
跟你說過多少次了
The doctor in clinic is Uncle A-Shui's son
衛生所的那個醫生是阿水伯的兒子
He's an acquaintance
是熟人
How can you let him do the operation?
你怎麼好意思去讓他裝
I didn't
我沒裝啦
I took pills!
這是吃的避孕丸啦
Pills, what pills?
避孕丸 避什麼丸
You always eat something nonsense
你每次吃那些有的沒有的
Never discuss with me
都不和我商量
Do you know what will happen after you take the pills?
你知道你吃了以後會怎麼樣
You can't have babies!
不會生
The doctor said it's safe
人家醫生說不會
Who said so?
誰說不會
Jin-ji's wife took the pills about 1 year
金吉的老婆吃了一年多
Now she can't have babies even if she wants to
現在要生生不出來了
Hey, Big Dragon
喂大頭龍啊
Come...
來
Take it
拿去
Drink it
喝下去
What are you afraid of?
你是在害怕什麼啦
They said it's effective on the first two months
人家說一兩個月喝還有效
Two days later, it will become blood
過兩天變成血水流出來就好了
Drink it!
喝下去嘛
You can have baby in future if you want!
要生以後再說嘛
After I have a job
等我找到工作
You can have as many babies as you want
你要生幾個就讓你生幾個
We can't afford a baby now
現在生下來拿什麼養人家
Right?
對不對
Drink it!
喝下去啦
Qun-Shu!
坤樹啊
The train is coming, hurry!
火車來了 快去啦
Boss, I cut this from a Japan magazine
老闆 這是我從一本日本雜誌上剪下來的
This is for advertisement
這就是專門替別人做廣告的那個
The Sandwich Man
三明治人
It's effective
這很有效
Your theater can try
你們戲院可以試試看
I won't charge you if it is useless
如果沒有效 我可以不拿錢
Boss, boss, see this
老闆 老闆你看
I can walk like this on the street
我可以像這樣在街上走來走去
People see me, me...
大家都看到我 我
I will dress like him
我前面跟他一樣
Wear your advertisement
掛你們戲院的電影廣告
People will see it
大家都看到
And your business will be better
你們的生意就比較好了
What is this?
這是什麼
The Sandwich Man
三明治人
Advertisement!
做廣告的
Will it be useful?
這哪會有效
Yes, sir, it is useful
有啦 老闆 這有效
Absolutely
絕對有效
If you don't believe it
你要是不信
You can hire me for one month
那你試用我一個月
If it doesn't work you don't have to pay me
要是沒有效 你不用給我錢
Sir, how are you?
阿伯啊 你好
A-chu!
阿珠
What are you doing?
你在做什麼
Tearing our blanket to make a custom
撕被單 做小丑的衣服
The theater owner said
戲院的老闆說
He'll hire me if I make my own clothes
衣服如果自己做 他就請我
$350 NTD a month without meals
一個月三百五 三餐吃自己
A-chu, I found a job
阿珠 我找到工作了
We can have the baby
孩子我們可以生下來了
A-chu
阿珠
He's the advertise man
那就是做廣告的那一個啦
Who's it?
誰啊
Kids?
孩子
Bastards!
臭小孩你
What are you doing?
你幹什麼
Run!
快跑
Here! Here!
在這 在這
Come, come, and run
來啊 來啊 趕快跑
You can't catch me!
捉不到 捉不到
Fuck!
你娘
Run! Run!
快走 快走
I'm here! I'm here!
我在這 我在這
Give it to me!
拿來
You can't catch me!
捉不到 捉不到
Catch me if you can
怎樣啦 來呀來呀
I'm not afraid of you! I'm not afraid of you!
不怕你啦 不怕你啦
What are you doing?
幹什麼
Well, don't let me get you
我跟你講 你就不要讓我抓到
No tea?
沒有茶了
Boss, I told you on the other day
老闆 那天我告訴你
About the new clothes...
要換一件新衣服的事 你說
What?
什麼啦
I told you on the other day
那天我跟你說過
The clothes is old and its color is fading
說這件衣服又破又褪色了
I need a new red one, it's more eye catching
看要換一件新的紅的 比較顯眼的
It might be more effective
可能比較有效果啦
Do you think the advertisement will be more useful?
你感覺這樣的廣告有效果嗎
I don't know
我也不知道耶
No matter you wear red, green,
反正你要換紅的 綠的
yellow, or black
黃的 黑的
That's your business
都是你家的事情
You said you will take care of the clothes
服裝的問題 是你當初自己說好的
Not mine
這和我都沒有關係
You are back
你回來了
Tea?
茶呢
Fuck, no tea in the theater!
你娘的 戲台沒茶
No tea at home!
家裏也沒茶
What are you doing?
你是在幹什麼
What's wrong with you?
你是怎麼啦
You hit tables when you come back
回來就敲椅子 敲桌子
And blame on me several times
一天罵我好幾遍
Bacause I want
恁爸高興啦
I can do whatever I want
要罵誰就罵誰
I am the boss!
在這我最大啦
Don't talk so loud
你別那麼大聲好不好
I can talk as loud as I want
我要多大聲就多大聲不行啊
What the hell
見到鬼了
You are mad when you're back
回來就兇巴巴的叫
What makes you mad?
不知道在兇什麼
We can make tea if there is no tea
沒茶再燒就好了
I wash a lot of clothes today
我一天洗那麼多衣服
But I did not complain
我也沒說什麼
Shout up, one more word
你給我閉嘴 你再說一句
I will slap you face
我就給你一巴掌
Uncle?
阿伯
You look like a geek in you dress
你這種打扮 人不像人鬼不像鬼
Who is your uncle?
誰是你的阿伯
I tried to find job
我也不是沒在找工作
But can't find any
可是都沒找到
Can't find any
找不到工作
So you dress like this?
你就打扮成這樣是不是
Listen,
我跟你說
as long as you try there are always chances
人家說肯做牛不怕沒有犁可以拖
You always try to do things in easy ways
你老想用投機取巧的方法
Of course you can't success
再多也找不到
I have no choices
我也是不得已的
When I am in trouble
當初困難的時候
You don't lend me rice
跟你借一升米都沒有
Do I owe you?
啊 我欠你的是不是
I'm not a rich man!
我不是有錢人
I earn my own living
我是賺多少吃多少
I have a family
我要養妻子兒女
I don't lend you my rice
我米不借你
So you wear like this
你就給我裝扮成這種模樣
Shame on you
來丟人現眼
Listen
我跟你說
If you keep wearing like this
如果你再繼續打扮成這樣
Move to other villages
乾脆到別的村子去
Don't live here and lose my face
不要住在這丟我的臉
Write your son's name?
寫你兒子的名字
I cannot read
我不識字啦
What's the name?
什麼名字
Hsu A-long
許阿龍
Which "long"
哪一個龍
The "long" for dragon in mandarin
鼠 牛 虎 兔 龍的龍
Born in February
二月生的
Why don't you come earlier?
怎麼不早一點來報出生
We just decided the name yesterday
昨天才取的名字的
You'll be fined $15 NTD for 3 months delay
超過三個月要罰十五塊哦
Ah! I...
啊 我
I don't know I have to report this
我就不知道要報出生啊
You don't know
不知道
Then how do you know how to have babies?
那你怎麼知道生孩子
A-long, do you miss daddy?
阿龍 你捨不得爸爸走是不是
See, my son loves me
你看 我兒子跟我最好
How do you know he loves you?
你真的以為他跟你最好
He doesn't recognize you
他才不認得你呢
What are you talking about?
你說什麼
When you went out in the morning
你早上出去的時候
He was either sleeping
他不是還在睡覺
Or on my back while I did the laundry
不然就被我背著在洗衣服
When he was awake, he saw a clown
等到他清醒 你就這張小丑的臉了
When you come back at night, he slept again
晚上你回來時他又在睡了
How can he recognize you?
他怎麼會認得你啦
He can't!
不認識啦
To him, you look like
他看你這樣
Like a big doll...
就像他的大玩偶
doll
大玩偶
I'm my son's big doll?
我是阿龍的大玩偶
A-long!
阿龍
I'm your big doll
爸爸是你的大玩偶呢
Shut up, shut up
不用說 不用說
Let's talk in police station
要講來去派出所講啦
I'm not afraid of you
我也不怕你啦
He hit a kid
撞到孩子還大小聲
Do you think he is right?
你看他有理嗎
He's making a fuss
還在那大小聲呢
Do you know how to drive?
你會不會開車啊
It would be okay if kid stayed away
小孩不要來玩米包也不會掉落
Now blame on kid again?
又講到孩子身上
Kid knows nothing
孩子哪裏知道什麼啦
Shut up, let's talk in police station
不用講 我們來去派出所講
Fuck you! Let's talk to your boss
很惡劣喔 叫你老闆來
Shut up, send your boss here!
不用講 叫你老闆來
Is A-long sleeping?
阿龍睡了啊
Yes!
嗯
The Smithy was on fire this morning, do you know that?
早上打鐵店火燒房子你知道嗎
I know
我知道
I passed the rice miller
我剛才走到米廠
A kid broke a leg
有一個小孩腿斷了
What happened?
怎麼樣
A car came to freight rice
有一台米車載米
Some rice packages fell and hit the boy
米包掉下來壓到他
Uh...
哦
You're back
回來了哦
Ah!
啊
Qun-Shu!
坤樹啊
You're advertisement is not working
我看你宣傳沒有效果
Don't do it anymore
乾脆不要做了啦
Can you ride a tricycle?
你會不會踩三輪車
I can't
我不太會
It's easy, just try
很簡單 踩幾次就會了
I think my theater
我想我這間戲院
Should advertise by tricycle
以後乾脆用三輪車做宣傳
What about me?
那 那我呢
Don't worry, you're still hired
你放心啦 照常用你
After riding the tricycle
每天踩三輪車回來以後
Come help in the theater
一樣來戲台幫忙
I will take you to the bike dealer tomorrow
明天我帶你到車行去牽車
Yes! Yes!
好 好
A-chu!
阿珠啊
Where's Qun-Shu?
啊你們坤樹呢
Qun-Shu?
坤樹
Qun-Shu isn't home. What do you want for him?
坤樹不在 你找坤樹什麼事
I'm going to Taipei, I want to sell him the tricycle
我要去台北 這台車想讓給他
This one... to Qun-Shu?
這台車 這台車要讓給我們坤樹
Yes!
對啦
How much?
差不多多少錢啊
Whatever
隨便啦
I don't need it anymore
反正我已經不要了
Is this true?
真的要讓給我們坤樹啊
Does Qun-Shu know?
坤樹知道嗎
I haven't told him yet
我還沒有跟他說
A-chu, your husband is back
阿珠 你先生回來了
Qun-Shu, you're back
坤樹 你回來了啊
Qun-Shu
坤樹我問你
Can you ride a tricycle?
你會不會踩三輪車
Ah... you knew it?
啊 你都知道了
Yes, Jin-ji told me
是啊 金吉都跟我說了
He said it's okay
他說剛開始不會沒關係
Just try several times, and you'll manage
多踩幾次就會了
What? Jin-ji?
啊 你說什麼 金吉
Right, he said, the tricycle he'll sell us in a good price
是啊 他說三輪車要便宜讓給我們
He wanted you to think about it
說讓你想想看
He'll meet you at the theater at night
晚上再去戲台找你
Jin-ji, is it OK?
金吉 這樣好嗎
Is it a bad thing?
這樣怎麼不好
If so...
這樣
you don't have to wear the make up
這樣你就不用去當小丑
Well, I mean I don't know
沒有啦 我是說不知道
How to resign from the boss
怎麼樣向老闆辭頭路
Why?
怎麼說
You see, were it not because of him
你想想看 當初要不是他肯用我
We might not have A-long
不一定我們現在
We might not afford a baby?
連阿龍都沒辦法生出來呢
Right?
對不對
If I have a new job
現在我一找到新的工作
And forget his help
就把人家的恩情忘記了
Can that be right?
這樣對嗎
What shall we do?
不然要怎麼辦
Don't worry
放心啦
Your husband is good
你丈夫有你丈夫的辦法
He will success, understand?
總有出頭的一天 知道嗎
Hey, where's my son?
喂 我兒子呢
He's sleeping
在睡啦
Big Dragon, here you are
大頭龍 你在這
Your dad is back and you're sleeping?
您爸回來了你還在睡
He's sucking
嘴巴還在吸一下 吸一下
What's wrong with your son?
你兒子怎麼這樣
Sleeping all day long
一天到晚就在睡覺
Wake up, and keep your dad company
起來啦陪你爸爸玩
Or I will ask your mom to wake you with water
不起來就叫你媽媽潑你水
New movie, new movie
好片來了 好片來了
Le-Gong theater will play the movie 3 days from today
從今天開始三天樂宮戲院演出
Orchids And My Love, Orchids And My Love
我女若蘭 我女若蘭
Played by Miss Pao-Yung Tang
本片由唐寶雲小姐主演
Don't forget
請大家不要忘記了
Good movie, good movie
好片來了 好片來了
Le-Gong theater will play the movie 3 days from today
今天開始三天樂宮戲院演出
Orchids And My Love is famous in South East Asia
我女若蘭本片轟動東南亞
and Taipei
轟動台北
Please don't forget
請大家不要忘記了
3 days only, 3 days only
三天而已 三天而已
Good movie, good movie
好片來了 好片來了
3 days from today
從今天開始三天
At Le-Gong theater
樂宮戲院演出
Orchids And My Love, Orchids And My Love
我女若蘭 我女若蘭
Played by Miss Pao-Yung Tang
本片由唐寶雲小姐主演
Don't forget
請大家不要忘記了
Good movie, good movie
好片來了 好片來了
Le-Gong theater will play the movie 3 days from today
今天開始三天樂宮戲院演出
Orchids And My Love, Orchids And My Love
我女若蘭 我女若蘭
The movie is famous in South East Asia
本片轟動東南亞
Uncle A-Shui, is he your nephew?
阿水伯 那不是你侄子嗎
Yes, yes
是啊 是啊
Young man, should be like this
年輕人 這樣也差不多
He's more mature now
他現在比較會想了
A-chu
阿珠啊
Are you nuts, speak so loud
著猴啊 喊那麼大聲
A-chu, what about this
阿珠 這樣可以嗎
Where's the money?
唉 錢呢
You still remember?
你還記得錢啊
Take it, you smiles when you see money
拿去 看到錢你就笑了
How much do you have?
這有多少啊
$350 NTD
三百五啦
I thought it is $400 NTD
不是說四百嗎
Not yet, you're dreaming
還沒啦 想得美
That's next month
那是下個月
Ha ha! Big Dragon!
哈哈 大頭龍啊
Your Dad is back
爸爸回來了
Did you behave yourself, my precious son
你有沒有乖 金子銀子
Did you bother your mother?
你有沒有吵你媽媽呢
What happened to your face, here, let me see
臉怎麼這個樣子 來來來
"Big Dragon never lose in fight."
大頭龍一粒珠打架不認輸
"Hit the bug with the bamboo stick."
拿竹竿打金龜
"The bug flies."
金龜一飛走
"Big Dragon fly the kite, kite..."
大頭龍放風箏 風箏
Hey, what's wrong? Crying?
喂 怎麼了 哭了
Here, let me hug you
來來 爸爸抱你喔
come
來
Why are you crying? Don't cry
哭什麼 別哭啦
Again, what's wrong?
再哭 怎麼了
Daddy is hugging you
爸爸抱你耶
You cry in my hug?
抱著了你還哭
You're not a good boy if keep crying, okay?
再哭不乖了 知道嗎
What's wrong, why does he keep crying?
怎麼了 怎麼一直哭
What did you do? Why does he keep crying?
你是怎麼逗他的 怎麼一直哭呢
Here, come to mommy
來 媽媽抱
I don' t know
我也不知道
I play with him and he started crying
就跟他玩 玩到一半他就哭了
I don't know why?
也不知道在番什麼
Good boy...
惜惜喔
He's daddy!
爸爸呢
Don't you recognize him?
爸爸你不認得了嗎
What's wrong with him?
阿龍今天怎麼了
Well, you always draw your face like a clown
沒有啦 就是你常常畫小丑臉
He can't recognize you without the make up
今天沒畫 他認不出來了
You can't recognize him, right?
不認得爸爸了喔 是不是
Good boy...
惜惜喔
Good, are you good?
乖 有乖乖沒有
A-long, are you good?
阿龍 有乖乖沒有
Cried so badly
唉唷 哭得這樣
He's daddy, daddy
這是爸爸耶 這是爸爸耶
Can't you recognize him?
你不認得了嗎
Daddy!
爸爸啦
He's not a stranger, he's daddy
他不是別人耶 是爸爸啦
Cry and laugh
一下子哭 一下子笑
A-long, good boy
阿龍好乖喔
Hum...
嗯嗯
Are you crazy? Why do you draw on your face?
你發瘋了 現在你畫臉幹嘛
I, I...
我 我就
I'm my son's big doll
是我兒子的大玩偶啦
Mei-Li
美麗
I brought you some tooth pastes and tooth brushes
我給你多拿了一些牙膏牙刷
Dad gave us some medicinal liquor
還有 這是爸爸送給我們的兩瓶補酒
Why does your dad always send these to us?
你爸爸怎麼老是送這些東西給我們
Isn't that your colleagues Wang Wu-Hsiung?
那是不是你的同事王武雄
Right!
是啊
Lin Zai-Fa
林再發
Yes!
嗯
If I were you
我要是你的話
I will not leave my wife to sell pots
我就不會離開老婆去賣這種鳥鍋
You don't know my situation
你不瞭解我的處境
As long as I work and make money
只要有工作 能夠賺錢
When the baby is born
等孩子生下來
I won't have to worry about money, right?
就不缺錢用了 對不對
During the training
受訓的時候
I found the job boring!
我就覺得這工作沒什麼意思
When I saw you in the training
看你的樣子 我總以為受訓的時候
I thought you will escape like others
你會跟其他人一樣開溜了呢
I planned to
本來我是打算開溜的
But I don't like to see
可是我實在不喜歡看到
my family worry for me
家裏人為我愁眉苦臉的樣子
Once I left my family
只要離開了家
I can do anything
什麼工作我都做得下去
Right, you know what
對啊 你不知道啊
When I retired from the army
我剛退伍的時候 寄履歷表啊
I sent lots of resumes like movie starts sent autographs
就跟電影明星發籤名照片一樣
Hurry! Hurry! The ball is there
快啦 快啦 球在那裏啦
Wait for me...
等我一下啦
Hey, kid
喂 小朋友
Can you move?
請你讓開一點好嗎
What do you want?
有事嗎
Are you looking for a ball?
找球是吧
Let's exchange, ok?
我們來交換好不好
I will give you the ball if you watch the warehouse for me
你幫我看倉庫 我把球還給你
Are you ready?
好了沒有
Wu-Hsiung, let's go!
武雄 走吧
Everyone, come and see our new invention
各位 請看我們最新的發明啊
The Japanese imported fast pot
日本原裝進口的快鍋啊
It can cooked the beef soft in 2 minutes
二分鐘之內就能把牛肉燉爛
Today I will demonstrate how to make porridge
今天跟大家示範的是煮稀飯
We all know
我們大家都曉得
Usually it takes 20 minutes to make porridge
平常煮稀飯呢 要用二十分鐘
But with this pot
用這個鍋煮呢
You only need 2 minutes
只要二分鐘就可以了
Just 2 minute, now...
二分鐘就可以了 現在
Come here!
回來 回來
No
不行啦
You can't cover it, it will explode
不能蓋 蓋了會炸的
Take off the clothe
把布拿起來
Don't bother, don't bother...
不要管了 不要管了
Water! Use water!
用水 用水啊
Come on...
什麼快鍋
We should use Taiwan pot
還不如用我們台灣的
It's safer
比較安全啦
Now open the pot
現在各位把快鍋打開
First we will introduce the outer pot
首先介紹的就是外鍋
It is for direct heating
就是直接加熱作用
You put food in the inner pot
這是內鍋 它是盛東西用的
The rubber is
這個就是附框橡皮圈 它的作用
to prevent the steam from evaporating
是為了防止鍋裏的水蒸氣外洩
Next...
接下來
Please
請
I... I was too slow to take notes
我 我的筆記來不及抄
Cuold you repeat?
可不可以請工程師再講一遍
OK, I will say it again
我現在再給各位講解一次
This is outer pot
這個就是外鍋
This is inner pot
這個呢 就是內鍋
This is rubber
這是附框橡皮圈
The most important part is
另外最重要的部份呢
This is siren
就是這個警聲器
Mates, please pay attention!
各位同學 要注意喔
When the sirens make sounds
當警聲器發出聲音
Means the pressure in the inner pot
就表示鍋內的壓力
has reached it's maximum
它已經達到它最大的安全範圍
At this time, if you don't turn off the fire
這個時候 如果你不把火關小的話
It will be very dangerous
它可能就會造成危險
Please!
請
Sir!
報告工程師
I just left the army
我剛退伍不久
I was in engineering troops
在部隊裏我幹的是工兵
I think asking a housewife to use the pot
我覺得要一個家庭主婦用這種東西
Is more dangerous than digging mines
比我們挖地雷還可怕
If you are not confident to our products
你對我們的產品沒有信心
How can you sell it?
怎麼能夠推銷我們的產品呢
You invent the pot
這東西是你發明的
Of course you are confident
你當然有信心
But what about us?
可是我們呢
Hey, no, no, no!
喂 不 不 不
I'm not that good
我沒有這麼了不起
The Japanese invented this
這是日本人發明製造的
They used it for ten or twenty years!
人家日本人已經用了一二十年了
We are starting to use this now!
而我們到現在才要用這種東西啊
Forget it! Lin Zai-Fa
算了吧 林再發
What the fuck are you writing?
你還寫這些狗屁幹嘛
The company may not read it
公司看不看還是個問題呢
Why won't they?
公司為什麼不看
Read? They sent us here
看 他們把我們送到這個地方來
They have cards in their sleeves
難道他們心裏會沒有數啊
We don't only work for the company,
我們工作 不只是為公司
but for ourselves
也是為我們自己
You can think that way
你才二十出頭
because you are in your early twenties
你可以這麼想
But I am in my thirties
可是我已經三十多了
I have a wife and will have a kid soon
我有老婆 也快有孩子了
I cannot think like you do
我可不能跟你有一樣的想法
Didn't the General Managers said...
總經理不是說
Taiwan have more than 2.5 million households
我們台灣目前有二百五十萬戶人家嗎
If every ten households buy a pot
如果每十戶買一隻快鍋的話
We can sell 250 thousand pots!
我們也可以賣二十五萬隻耶
You still believe them?
你還相信他們那些鬼話啊
250 thousand is a joke!
二十五萬隻 開玩笑嘛
It's too early to give up now!
現在就失望未免言之過早吧
Lin Zai-Fa
林再發
Sometimes, to be confident or to be fooled
有的時候信心和受騙
Is like two sides of one coin
就只差一張衛生紙之隔
You might be right
你說的也許是對的
But I tried hard to get this job
不過 我好不容易才找到這份工作
Mei-Li's family always tease me
美麗家裏的人一直在取笑我
They went against us before our marriage
從結婚前就反對我們在一起
And put me under pressure
唉 給了我精神上很大的壓力
It's hard to find a job
工作又那麼難找
So I think selling pot
所以 我倒是覺得推銷快鍋這份工作
is doable
確實是可以做的
Perhaps we will succeed -Hey
或許我們會成功的 -喂
Kid, wait
小朋友 你等一下
Kid
小朋友
I want to thank you to watch over the warehouse
謝謝你那一天幫我們看倉庫
This is for you
這個東西送給你
See
你看
On the top is a laughing Buddha
這上面有個笑哈哈大肚彌勒佛
I made it myself
是我自己刻的
It is his navel
這是它肚臍眼
I accidentally broke it when craving
我刻的時候不小心把它刻破了
I can see you from the hole
從這肚臍眼可以看到你哦
See that?
看到沒有
Take it
送給你
What are you looking at?
你在看什麼啊
Hey, young man
喂 年輕人
Sit here, it's cooler
在那邊坐 比較涼快
Young man, what is this?
年輕人 這是什麼東西
Thermo pots
快鍋啊
Thermo pots? What is that?
快鍋 快鍋是什麼東西
It cooks with thermal energy
快鍋就是利用溫度跟壓力的原理
What are you talking about? I don't understand
你在說什麼 我都聽不懂
For instance, when we cook beef or pork knuckle
譬如說我們煮牛肉豬腳
It usually takes two hours, right?
本來要兩個小時對不對
Right!
是
With this it only takes 10 minutes
現在用這個只要十分鐘就可以了
You can cook it well, it's time saving
很快就可以爛 又節省時間
Why do you want to save time?
煮那麼快幹什麼
It takes time to cook
煮東西要慢慢煮
or it won't taste well
味道才有出來
Shit! The bird droppings on my head
操他媽的 鳥屎掉在我頭上了
It brings bad luck to young men
年輕人 滴到鳥屎會倒楣
You need to have some pork knuckle noodle
回家要吃豬腳麵線
What is he talking about?
他說什麼
He said "bird shit brings bad luck."
他說鳥屎掉在頭上運氣不好
You will need to eat pork knuckle noodle
回去要吃豬腳麵線
What the hack?
哪有這種事
Hey, he might be right
喂 他說的也許是真的
Luck is not on us recently
你看我們最近運氣老是不好
We can't sell any pot
快鍋也都推銷不出去
Think about it
你想想看
We tried many ways
我們利用很多方法都沒有效
Listen, what about this?
你看這個樣子好不好
Let's sell the pot in cheap price
我們把這些快鍋拿去半價賤賣
And escape with the money
拿了錢我們就溜了嘛
Don't make jokes
別開玩笑
Wu-Hsiung
武雄
Perhaps we used wrong approaches
我認為我們推銷的方式好像不大對
Let's do this
這樣子好了
We always sell together
過去我們老是用單線推銷
We should sell in two ways
現在我們改用雙線進行
Let's sell separately
兩個人分開來推銷
By this way
這樣子推銷
We might have better performances
效果可能會比較大一點
What do you think?
你認為怎麼樣
Hey! Hey! Kid!
喂 喂 小朋友
Kid
小朋友
What do you want?
你要吃什麼
Seafood noodle!
三鮮面
And you?
那你呢
Pork knuckle noodle...
豬腳麵線
and a egg!
加個蛋啊
Pork knuckle noodle and a egg?
豬腳麵線 加蛋
Young man, have some gram soup
年輕人 吃綠豆湯
Thank you! Thank you!
謝謝 謝謝
You can more if you want!
吃完再盛啊
Want some more?
要不要喝一點
OK!
嗯
Well?
怎麼樣
Have you sell any pot yet?
賣出去第一隻快鍋了沒有
Such a nice pot
這麼好的快鍋
I don't know why no one want it?
怎麼會沒有人要 真搞不懂
Yes, here's a letter on your desk
對了 桌上有你的一封信
Madam, the bowl
歐巴桑 碗還你
Leave it on the table
隨便放在桌子上就好了
Thank you!
謝謝
Come! Come!
過來啦 過來啦
How can I help you?
有事嗎
My dad said I shouldn't take gifts from others
我爸爸說不要隨便拿別人的東西
You are a good girl!
你 你是一個聽話的乖小孩呀
She said she wants to see the shell
她說要來看貝殼
It's you, not me
才不是我啦 是你
It's you
是你啦
Wait a second, I'll take it
你們等一下 我去拿
The Buddha
跟你講 那個彌勒佛
Is made by that uncle
是那個叔叔自己刻的
There is a hole, it's funny
它上面有個洞 好好玩喔
I did not lie to you!
我沒騙你吧
See the belly
你看看它的肚子
What are you laughing at?
你們在笑什麼
Nothing!
沒有啦
Are you laughing at its naval?
笑它的肚臍是不是
No...
不是
What's your name?
你叫什麼名字
Chang Chung-Hwei
張瓊惠
And she?
那她呢
Don't tell him -Lee Shiao-Chi
不要講 -李小琪
Lee Shiao-Chi -Busybody, I told you not to tell
李小琪 -雞婆 叫你不要講
Why do you tell?
你還要講
It's fine
跟人家說沒有關係啦
Lee Shiao-Chi
李小琪
Can I call you Vick?
以後我叫你小琪好不好
Why do you like to wear hats?
你為什麼喜歡戴個帽子呢
Vick! Vick!
小琪 小琪
Why didn't you go to school today?
你今天怎麼沒上學呢
Why don't you want to see the shell?
你現在怎麼不到我那邊看貝殼了
Answer him!
說話呀
Okay!
好
I found I like here
我發覺我很喜歡這個地方
I like the people and view here
包括這裏的人 這裏的風景
The old days of smoking in sunset at Da-Dan county
現在大丹鄉一起抽煙看日落的情景
Is far away from me
竟然像我離開這裏好遠一樣
Were it not for selling the thermo pots
要不是為了推銷這些快鍋
I won't leave home away
我也不會到這離家一兩百里的地方
And I won't meet Vick
更不會認識小琪了
Are you still thinking of the 10-year plan?
你還在想十年計劃是不是
How strange?
奇怪
I found myself really like to see Vick
我發覺我很喜歡看到李小琪
Every time I saw her
可是每次看到她的時侯
I have strange feelings
心裏總覺得怪怪的
It seems like her family was misfortunate
好像她家曾經發生了什麼不幸的事
I heard her Mom died
我聽說她媽媽死了
But I don't know why
可是不知道什麼原因
Well, don't over think
好了 不要胡思亂想了
I wrote the work report for the company
這是我給公司寫的工作報告
Check if it is alright
你看看有什麼問題沒有
I will cook the pork knuckle with thermo pot tomorrow
我打算明天用快鍋燉豬腳
I will demonstrate there
當場示範給他們看
And treat free food
燉好了免費分送給大家吃
What do you think?
你看好不好
Two times a day, morning and afternoon
這個上下午各一場
The cost is $120 NTD for once, $240 NTD for twice
一場一百二 兩場兩百四
Two of us will need $480 NTD
兩個人加起來要四百八
Will the company agree?
公司肯嗎
We can try
我們可以先試一試
If the company doesn't agree
公司不肯的話
We won't do it next time
我們下次不做
I also want to help the company
其實我也是為公司著想
To sell the pots soon
很希望快鍋可以早點推銷出去
We can get more commission
我們可以多領點獎金
If so
這樣子的話
Mei-Li won't have to
美麗也就不必天天挺個大肚子
work in the beauty shop in pregnancy
到美容院去上班了
Wu-Hsiung, here's the pork knuckle
武雄啊 豬腳已經買好了
I'll leave it on the table
放在桌子上
Clean it yourself
你自己拔毛啊
I'm leaving
我走了
Oh...
哦
Bye!
再見啊
Will see...
就看今天了
What?
什麼啊
What thermos?
是什麼快鍋啊
I don't know! They said...
不知道啦 剛才就在講
Mom! Wait for me!
媽 等我 我要去啦
Hurry... Hurry...
快啊 快啊
Someone is making pork knuckle...
有人煮豬腳
Don't be so gluttonous
好啦 這麼愛吃
Don't push! Don't push!
別擠啦 別擠啦
Where can I put the gas tank?
這瓦斯桶要放哪
Leave it there..., leave it there...
放那 放那
Vick!
小琪
Come
過來啊
Can you clean the pork knuckle?
你會不會拔豬毛
My hands hurt
我手拔得好酸啊
Can you help me?
你來幫我拔一下好不好
Vick! Here, sit...
小琪啊 來 坐
Sit
坐
Vick
小琪
This is your gift, a new shell
這是我送給你的新貝殼
What thermos pot?
這是什麼快鍋
This is from Japan
這是日本的
You cook with this?
這要用來煮飯哦
Hey, excuse me, excuse me
喂 借過一下 借過
How do you cook without electricity?
啊沒電是要怎麼煮
It's the pork knuckle
真的是豬腳耶
Vick, after the cigarette
小琪 等抽完這根煙
I'll take over
剩下的我來拔
Put the pork knuckles
先放豬腳
And add some fresh green
再放點蔥花
Soy sauce
醬油
And add some MSG
然後再來點味精
OK, cover the pot
好 再把鍋蓋蓋起來
Now, turn on the fire
好 我們現在開始點火
Thanks! Thanks!
來 謝謝 謝謝
Please consider...
請參考
Thank you!
謝謝
Vick
小琪
It's 11!
十一分了
Call 911
快去叫警察啦
A-Yin, where are you?
阿英啊 你在哪裏
Special delivery
限時信
Zai-Fa
再發 我好害怕
I was afraid to tell you
本來是不想告訴你的
After leaving the beauty shop yesterday
可是昨天我從美容院下班
I fell in my way home
不小心在路上跌了一跤
I found myself bleeding when reaching home
回到家裏我發現下部出血了
I had an injection in the hospital
我到醫院去打針
The doctor said, tomorrow if I kept bleeding
醫生說 如果明天要是還出血
I'll need to see him again
再去找他
This morning, it still bleeds
今天早上起來下部還有血
I'm so scared
所以我好害怕
I know you are like me
我知道你跟我一樣
We really expect
我們是多麼盼望下個月
To have a baby next month
能生出一個寶寶來
Zai-Fa
再發
You just started your new career
你才接下這個工作不久
It's difficult to take a day off
不便請假回來
But I'm very scared
但是我心裏很害怕
I really need you
我很需要你回來一趟
Please forgive my unreasonable request
請原諒我無理的要求
Didn't you say your colleague Mr. Wang
你不是說跟你一起工作的王先生
is nice to you?
對你很好嗎
Can you ask him to replace you for two days?
就請他代你辛苦兩天好不好
We'll pay pack in future
我們以後再報答他
Please say thank to him for me
也代我謝謝他
All the best
祝你平安
Hello
您好
This is the junior secretary to the ambassador of America
我是美國大使的初級秘書
Yes, this is Cournel Grey. Is the ambassador...
您好 我是格雷上校 請問大使
Oh, Cournel Grey
格雷上校您好
No, he won't be in this morning
不 大使今天早上不在
Well, I had an accident with my car this morning
我今天早上出車禍了
Oh, I've already heard about your accident
我有聽說了
Don't worry
別擔心
I can handle matters like these
我能處理這種狀況
Yeah, but the guy I hit...
但是我撞到的那個人
Is he a labor?
他是勞工嗎
Well, as far as...
就我所知
Is he?
他是嗎
Is he a labor, or isn't he?
是或不是
Yes. As far as I know, he is
就我所知 他是勞工
Listen, this is an Asian country with which we have the
你聽好 這是一個與美國有著
closest cooperation and friendship
最緊密合作關係與邦交的亞洲國家
So I don't think there should be any problem
所以我想不會有什麼問題
However, the president would be very unhappy
不過 如果我們跟當地人或政府
if there was any trouble with any of the local people
有什麼問題
Or the government
我想總統會不太高興
Well, that's binding good
那是邦交關係
But what do I do?
但我應該怎麼做
I'll take care of the details
這件事就交給我來處理
You take the family to the hospital
你先帶傷患的家人去醫院
and I'll meet you there
我們醫院見
OK?
好嗎
Well, yeah, but I don't speak Chinese
好 但是我不會說中文
That's okay
沒關係
I'll have a foreign affairs police man accompany you
我會請負責外國事務的警察陪你去
Alright?
好嗎
Ok
好吧
Here!
這裏
This way!
這邊走
You know this is an ideal place for kids to play hide and seek
這個地方好適合小孩玩捉迷藏
I have the same feeling
我也有同感
Their new homes are nearly completed
他們的新家快蓋好了
Those apartments, over there, are new ones
那邊的公寓 是新建的
Once they've moved these people out
一旦他們將這些人遷出去
They're going to put up a high rise here
他們就要在這裏蓋大廈
Yeah
嗯
Should we ask someone?
我們要不要問人
It's okay
沒關係
Hey, kid
喂 小妹妹
Do you know
你知不知道新生北路二段
where No. 8-8, Avenue 28, Sec.2, Hsing Sheng North Rd. Is?
二十八巷八號之八在哪裏
Do you know where Jiang A-Fa lives?
那江阿發住哪裏你知不知道
Oh, my god!
哦 我的天啊
Hey, right there!
喂 在那裏
Let's go
走吧
Excuse me, is here
請問一下 你們這裏是
8-8, Avenue 28,
新生北路二段
Sec.2, Hsing Sheng North Rd?
二十八巷八號之八嗎
Is Jiang A-Fa your husband?
江阿發是你先生嗎
Jiang A-Fa is your father
江阿發是你爸爸
It's here
就是這裏
Madam, I'm terribly sorry
女士 我很抱歉
But there's been a terrible accident with your husband
你先生發生了很嚴重的意外
Jiang A-Fa had a car accident
江阿發先生今天早上
in front of the Taiwan Tobacco & Lliquor Corp. This morning
在公賣局出車禍了
He was hit
撞傷了
What did you say?
你在說什麼
Tell your mother
你跟你媽說一下
Your father had a car accident
你爸出車禍撞傷了
What is he talking about?
他是在說什麼
He said, dad...
他說阿爸
What happened, tell me...
阿爸怎麼了 還不快說啊
Dad had a car accident
阿爸被車撞到了
Car accident?
什麼 被車撞到
Where is he? Is he OK?
人在哪裏 要不要緊
He's fine now
沒有關係
He is in the hospital
現在已經送到醫院去了
He's okay
沒什麼問題的
I'm here to take you to the hospital
我是來帶你們到醫院去的
What is he talking about?
他到底在說什麼
He's telling us not to worry
他說不要擔心啦
Dad is in the hospital now, he's here to...
現在阿爸在醫院 他是來
Shit!
要死了
He's fine this morning
早上出門人還好好的
Don't know how badly injured was he
現在不曉得被撞得怎麼樣了
Don't worry
別擔心啦
What a bad luck
怎麼那麼歹運啦
Got hit by a car for no reason
無緣無故會被車撞到
She is soaking wet, help her take this off
這麼濕 快幫她解下來
Is she your sister?
這是你妹妹嗎
Is he your brother?
這是你弟弟嗎
It's her sister and brother
這是她的弟弟和妹妹
Oh, Jesus!
天啊
How many other children does he have?
他到底有幾個小孩啊
Jiang A-Ji, Jiang A-Ji
江阿吉 江阿吉
What month is this month?
現在是幾月了
May
五月
Great! When will the semester start?
很好 我們是幾月開學的
March
三月
March? You are still sleepy
三月 我看你還沒睡醒吧
The semester started in February, remember?
我們是二月開學的記不記得啊
It has been 3 months
現在都過三個月了
Why didn't you pay your fee?
你的代辦費怎麼還不交啊
I forgot to bring it
忘記帶了
Did you bring your lunch box?
你的便當帶了沒有
Yes, it's in the rice steaming box
帶了 拿去蒸了
OK! Everyone quiet
好 大家安靜
Our lesson this week is mutal aid
這一周 我們的公訓德目是互助
Mutual aid means help each other
互助就是互相幫助
You should help your classmates
同學當中有困難
When they encounter difficulties
大家就應該幫助他
A-Ji!
阿吉
Who are you looking for?
你找誰啊
I'm Jiang A-Ji's sister
我是江阿吉的姊姊
My dad had a car accident
我爸爸出車禍
He was hit by an American car
被美國車撞到了
Is he OK?
有沒有怎麼樣
I don't know
我不知道
OK! Wait
好 你等一下
Jiang A-Ji
江阿吉
Pack your bag and go home with your sister now
你趕快收拾書包跟你姐姐回家
OK! Let's start our lesson
好 現在我們開始上課
Take out your Chinese textbook
大家把國語課本拿出來
Bye teacher!
老師再見
Where is A-Chung's classroom?
阿忠教室在那裏
Over there!
在那邊
Mrs. Jiang, don't bring any more stuff
江太太 你不要再拿了
We should go now
我們可以走了
The hospital has things you need.
這些醫院裏面都有
Sister! I don't want to go to school
姐 我不要上學了
Don't you dare to tell mom!
你敢講這種話不怕被媽打死
We don't have money to pay
我們沒有錢交代辦費
Every time the teacher punish me to stand outside the class
每次工藝時間都被老師罰站
When Dad has money
等爸爸有錢
He will pay!
爸爸就會交了呀
Dad always says so
爸爸每次都說這句話
The teacher said the semester is going to end
老師說這學期快要結束了
It's fine, be patience
沒關係 忍耐一點
We will have money
等我賣去當養女
since they sell me
家裏就會有錢了
They will sell you?
你要被賣去當養女
Yeah, it's true this time
嗯 這一次是真的了
Dad was hit by a car
爸爸給車撞了
What about A-Chung?
阿忠呢
Let's go, Mom must be worried, hurry
走 媽一定急死了 快
Children are so young
孩子還那麼小
That true!
就是嘛
We are unlucky recently!
最近實在有夠歹運啦
Don't worry!
你不要操心啦
It will be fine
會沒事啦
Come, come!
啊 來啊 來啊
Hurry, hurry!
快點啦 快點啦
Faster, faster!
快點 快點
Here!
來
Tell if something happen
有事 你就回來說
You sit on the back
你們坐後面
Okay, please help
好啦 就拜託了
Hurry
快點
It seems that dad is hit by this car
好像是這部車撞到爸爸的
It's huge!
好大台喔
OK, OK, stop looking from here
好了好了 不要在這裏看了
Go, go...
你們通通回去 回去
Sit well
你們快坐好
Let's go
上車啦
What shall we do?
叫我們母子怎麼辦才好啦
Fine, fine, Mrs. Jing
好了好了 江太太
Don't be so sad
不要再哭得太傷心了
Mr. Jiang might be slight scarped
江先生說不定只是一點撞傷
If you kept crying
但是要是你一直這麼哭下去的話
His injury might go worse
會使他變得更嚴重
Perhaps he'll die
說不定會死掉喔
A-Ji is in the American car
阿吉在坐美國車
Cool! It's huge!
好棒哦 好大喔
Jiang A-Ji where are you going?
江阿吉你要去哪裏啊
Jiang A-Ji! Wait for us!
江阿吉 等等我們啊
I asked you not to be sad
叫你不要愁眉苦臉
We'll arrive Taipei soon
台北馬上就到了
How many times should I tell you?
我要說幾遍你才會聽得清楚
I do this for your sake
我會這樣做也是為了你們好
They said there are more opportunities in Taipei
人家說台北的機會比較好
If I have a chance...
要是給我碰到什麼好機會
Our kids are still studying
我們的孩子都在讀書
It will be better if they study in Taipei
去台北讀書的環境也比較好
I heard there're places that teach mutes to talk
聽說台北也有教啞巴說話
If have make money
要是我賺到錢
I want to take our mute kid go
我也要帶我們這啞巴孩子去學說話
So you don't need to
也不用你為了我們這個啞巴孩子
worry for our mute kid
煩惱一輩子
Here we are, here we are
到了 到了
Good morning, Sir!
早安 長官
Good morning, can you open the gate?
早安 請把門打開
We are in a bad hurry today
我們趕時間
Aye aye, Sir!
是的
How is he?
怎麼樣
Mr. Jiang is not in danger
江先生沒有什麼生命危險
He just broke his legs
只是兩條腿斷了
He is in the surgery now
現在啊 正在手術
He will come out soon
等一等就會出來
What did he say?
說什麼
He said dad is alright
他說阿爸沒有什麼關係
This way, please
來 這邊請
Come, here
走 來
Please have a seat
來 裏面請坐
Wait there
你們先到這邊等一下啊
Let's have a look
我們先出去看
Mom is there!
媽媽在那邊
Let's play
我們先出去玩啊
Hurry, hurry!
快啊 快點 快
OK!
好啦
Mom, does Dad live here?
阿母 阿爸是要住在這裏嗎
How do I know?
我怎麼知道
How long will he live?
要住多久
Naughty girl, what are you thinking about?
死丫頭 你在高興什麼
Nothing, I want to use the rest room
沒有啦 我很想上廁所
Me, too
我也是一樣
I haven't pee from this morning
尿從早上態到現在
I don't know where is the toilet?
也不知道要去哪裏上
Neither do I
我也不知道
Where is A-Ji?
阿吉他們去哪裏啊
A-Ji!
阿吉啊
A-Ji, come
阿吉 來啦
You are bold
你們實在好大膽
How dare run around
這是什麼地方 也敢在這亂跑
Don't you worry the Americans may catch you?
不怕被美國人捉走
We went to the restroom
我們去上廁所
Where?
在哪
Over there, over there!
在那裏 在那裏
Go! Let's go
走 我們快去
Over here!
在這裏
Sit on the coach
你們回去沙發上坐
Don't run around
不要再亂跑有沒有聽到
OK
好
Go
快去
Go, get in
走 進去
My god
要死了
The toilet is so clean and white
這廁所這麼乾淨 這麼白
Mom, should I sit or squat on the stool
媽 這廁所是要用蹲還是要用坐的
I don't know
我也不知道
Let's try to squat
不然用蹲的試試看
Ah...
啊
I'm sorry, sorry
對不起 對不起
Mom, what's wrong?
阿母 你怎麼了
A rude American came in
一個美國人好大膽
He did not knock
他也沒有敲門啦
He blamed me did not lock the door
還說我門不鎖起來
Brother, why is it white everywhere
哥 這裏怎麼全部都是白白的
Because this is the American hospital
因為這裏是美國醫院啊
The chairs, the windows
你看椅子白的 窗戶白的
The wall and lights are white
牆壁白的 電燈也是白的
Even the toilet paper is white
衛生紙也是白的
The stool is white
還有小便的地方也是白的
A-Fa...
阿發啊
Be careful now, easy, be careful...
小心啊 慢慢來 小心
Brother, is the white man our Dad?
哥 那個白白的也是爸爸
Yes!
對啊
A-Fa!
阿發啊 阿發啊
A-Fa, are you OK?
你要不要緊啊
Nurs, I'll be back
護士 我等一下回來
You two can go now, I'll take care of him
你們兩個先忙吧 我來照顧他
Yes, sister
好的 修女
My God! What happened to you?
哎呀 怎麼把你撞成這樣啦
A-Fa! What should we do?
阿發啊 這樣怎麼辦啦
What should we do?
我們要怎麼辦才好啦
A-Fa... A-Fa...
阿發啊 阿發
Mrs. Jiang, please don't worry
江太太 你不要擔心啦
Your husband surgery went well
你先生手術很順利
He will be recover soon
馬上就會醒過來
I speak Taiwanese
我會說閩南話
My name is Maria
我叫做瑪莉亞
I work in monastery
我是在聖母院工作
I'm here to serve Mr. Jiang
現在特別調來這裏為江先生服務
Don't worry
你們放心啦
Mr. Jiang will be able to leave after several months
江先生調養幾個月就可以出院了
Several months!
幾個月啊
So you are asking us not to eat?
你叫我們全家的人都不要吃飯啊
How should we live?
你是要叫我們吃什麼啦
A-Fa, A-Fa
阿發 阿發喔
You are unlucky
你怎麼這麼歹運啦
God! Why don't the American hit me
要死了 美國人怎麼不來撞我
But you!
會去撞你啦
A-Fa!
阿發啦
How misfortunate am I!
我歹命我歹命喔
Mom, don't cry
阿母 別哭了
The sister had left!
修女跑掉了啦
So what?
她走了有什麼關係
What the hell are you doing?
你叫我是要死了
Listen!
我告訴你喔
You father was seriously hit by car
你阿爸被車撞成這樣
Open your eyes to learn the situation here!
你眼睛睜亮一點 給我覺悟一點
So are you
還有你們兩個也一樣
Your dad can not work
你阿爸沒辦法工作了
Don't go to school from tomorrow
明天開始不要上學了
Go to work!
去做工
OK!
好
What are you laughing at?
你是在笑什麼
What are you laughing at? It's same to you
有什麼好笑 你也一樣啦
A-Fa, are you awake?
阿發 你醒了是嗎
Are you OK?
要不要緊
What happened to my legs?
我的腳是怎麼了
They are broken
兩隻腳都斷了
So they fixed with plaster
現在全上著石膏了
Fine, I thought I'm dead
我還以為死了 還好
Where are the kids?
小孩呢
They are all here
全來了
Here, come!
來 過來
Dad!
阿爸
Where am I?
這是什麼地方
American hospital
美國醫院
How do we pay?
我們要去哪裏找那麼多錢啊
I don't know
我也不知道
An American
是一個美國人
and a cop brought us here
和我們的警察帶我們來的
What did he say?
他有沒有說什麼
He left without a word
他什麼也沒說就出去了
Now...
現在
What should we do?
看現在要怎麼辦啦
I told you
當初我就跟你說
Works are the same everywhere
如果要工作 在哪裏都一樣
But you want to go here
你就偏偏要來這個地方
And you said women are innocent
還說我女人不懂事
Said you might be lucky
說不一定會碰到什麼好運
As I see, you are lucky
我看 你現在是碰到好運了
Very Lucky!
碰到一個大好運了啦
Mr. Jiang you are awake
江先生你醒了
Mrs. Jiang, we brought some food
江太太 我給你們帶了點吃的來了
We have sandwiches
這裏頭有三明治
milk, soda, and apples
有牛奶 有汽水 還有蘋果
Mr. Jian
江先生
This is Mr. Gray
這位就是格雷上校
You were hit by his car
就是他車撞到你的
He's sorry and hope you can forgive him
他非常抱歉 請你原諒
And hope you can cooperate with us
同時請你盡量跟我們合作
It's you, alas!
就是你啊 哎呀
You were so uncareful!
你開車也太不小心了
Your car is so big
你車子那麼大
And you drove so fast
又開得那麼快
I saw your car from far away
我在遠遠就看到你了
I tried to avoid your car
我一直躲一直躲
But you still bumped on me
你也偏偏把我撞過來
Since you bumped on me
現在撞到了
All reasons are useless!
再說什麼也沒有什麼用啦
Not only me that you broke,
你撞的不只是我一個人
but all my family!
我整個家庭都被你撞得亂七八糟了
What did he say?
他說什麼
He is very upset, he blams you for the accident
他很煩惱 在責怪你這場車禍
Oh, I see
哦 我知道了
You speak Chinese
你會說中國話
May I talk to you for minutes please...
我可以跟你談一下嗎
Nurs, can you help me out and translate to the family my feelings
請你幫忙把我的想法翻譯給他們
First of all, I'd like to take responsibility for the accident
我會盡量幫助他們家庭負起責任
Here's money, and you give to them I would appreciate...
這一點錢表示我的歉意
He asked you not to worry
他說請你放心
In addition to the US insurance company,
除了美國保險公司會賠償你們外
Captain Grey himself will pay you, too
格雷上校他自己也會負責任
Your family will be fine
不會讓你們全家的生活發生問題
You can take the money first
這是上校的小意思 你先拿去用
I will give you more later
以後我會再給你們
Besides, with your agreement,
另外上校徵求你們的同意
Captain hopes to send your daughter
想要把你們這個女兒
to study in US
送到美國讀書
You are lucky
這次是你們運氣好
To be hit by Captain
撞到格雷上校的車
If it were other people
要是撞到別的車啊
You might still be lying on the street
說不定現在還躺在路邊呢
Thank you..., thank you...
謝謝啊 謝謝啊
Sorry, sorry
對不起 對不起
Sorry
對不起
Excuse me
借問一下
May I know Jiang A-Fa
那個被車撞到的江阿發
lives in which room?
不知道是住幾號房？
What did you say?
你說什麼
Like me, the worker
跟我一樣做工的那個
Whom was bomped by the car
被車撞到那一個
Do you understand what he said?
你知道他說什麼嗎
I don't understand the word
我不懂他說什麼
I'm sorry I have no idea what you said
我很抱歉 我不懂你說什麼
I'm sorry I can't help you
我不能幫忙你
It's cozy!
這麼舒適哦
How was it?
問得怎麼樣
He doesn't understand me and I don't understand him
她說的我不懂 我說的她不懂
Come, come, come
來 來 來
Remember
大家記著
When you get in
大家等一下一起進去
Don't be cheated, show your attitude
不要被唬了 要裝個樣子
Tell them your needs
條件一條一條要開出來
Otherwise
要不然
Bumpkin, A-Fa, almost died
阿發這個鄉巴佬被撞得半死不活
He lose his hands and feet
斷手斷腳
But only have three packages of rice in return
只抱三包米回家去吃一輩子
Remember what to do
要記得這樣做
Yes! Okay!
對 好
Boss, cop
工頭 警察
Officer
警察先生啊
I'm A-Fa's boss
我是阿發的工頭啊
My A-Fa was bumped by American
我的阿發被美國人撞到
It's him
是他撞的
It's him!
就是他哦
A-Fa and his wife has a big family to raise
阿發他的太太小孩一大堆
They count on A-Fa's salary
就是靠這個阿發賺工錢
Listen
我跟你講
I did not hit him
人又不是我撞的
It's no use to tell me
你跟我講也沒有用
You should tell him
我帶你去跟他說
Listen, kids
你們這些小孩
Listen
都給我聽清楚
Who tell others how much we have
誰要出去跟別人說我們有多少錢
I will sew your mouth one by one
我就把你們的嘴一個一個縫起來
Understand?
聽到沒有
Yes!
有啦
Collect the bottles
把那些汽水瓶收一收
We can sell to garbage collector
拿回去賣破鐵
OK!
好
A-Fa...
阿發
Uncle...
阿伯
A-Fa now you sit on the rice bucket
阿發你現在坐在米桶上面
Hands in the money box
手放在錢盒裏
You can eat when lying
躺著都有的吃了
but we have to work like slave-dogs
不像我們做牛做馬曬得黑漆漆的
What are you talking about?
你是在說什麼
Why don't I understand?
我怎麼都聽不懂
Come on, you have 50 thousand cash
別裝了 你現在有現金五萬
You mute daughter can study in America
你的啞巴女兒可以去美國留學
Who told you?
誰說的啦
Come on!
還用誰說
I'm the boss
我做工頭是做假的
If something happen to my man
我自己的兄弟有什麼事
I have to know
我當然要去打聽才行
Well
沒有啦
The American is a nice man
那個美國人做人也很不錯
A-Fa
阿發
Were it because you saw the American was driving
你是不是看到那個美國人開車
So you hit the car yourself in purpose?
故意去撞的
Shit, A-Shiung, what are you talking about?
要死了 阿雄你是在說什麼
Fuck
你媽的
You can have this if you like
你若是要 這給你
You can find an American
你不會去找一個美國人開的車
and try it yourself
撞撞看
I'm kidding, don't be mad!
說笑的 別生氣啦
I don't have the luck
我腦袋尖尖那有那個福氣
I like to make jokes
說笑說習慣了
Come on!
就是這樣嘛
You have a good life now
你現在好命了
Wearing necklace and dress in new clothes!
每天戴項鏈 穿新衣去玩喔
That's not true!
哎唷 哪有好命
See how many kids I have
你看我那些小孩一群跟粽子一樣
Life will never be easy for me!
好命 哎唷 下輩子吧
Behave yourself
哦 乖乖哦
You can have the banana
你們想要吃香蕉拿去吃啦
We don't want banana, we want to have apples
我們不要吃香蕉 我們要吃蘋果
No! Mom said the apples are for god
不行啦 給阿母先拿回去拜拜
You can have it later
拜好了再給你們吃
It's fine
不要緊了
I never had apples in my life
一輩子也沒吃過蘋果
Go, one for each of you
來 一個人去拿一個來吃
It's for you
你吃啦
My feet hurts, you eat it!
我腳痛不想吃 你吃吧
Mom, how do we eat this?
阿母 這整個要怎麼吃
Like people in TV
像電視一樣
An apple worths 4 packages of rice
一顆蘋果差不多可以換四斤米
Don't you know how to eat Apples? Hurry!
這樣也不會吃 快吃啊